this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software digital ocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size we're
moving infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco
/ SC radio hello everyone this is Felina
for SP radio today I'm here with me I
have regarding Terrell he is a software
engineer and a Microsoft MVP who is
passionate about functional programming
he's active in the F sharp community and
he started to washington DC f sharp user
group he's also the author of the many
book concurrency end of nets modern
patterns of currents and parallel
programming
he believes in pulling up programming as
mechanism for finding a right tool for
the job
welcome to the show Ricky - inna thank
you for anything I made excitedly here
thanks so the topic of today's show is
concurrency because that's also what
your book is about any word you are an
expert on first things first what is
concurrency all right well concurrency
you capable to currency as a real a
programming model where there are more
than one computation that is acute it in
like in overlap in time like
interleaving fashion in really simply
you can think is a concurrency the
capability where several tasks
Coran at the same time but what would I
like to think about concurrency is a
step forward is really a way where you
can structure your program is solution
to solve a problem that may or may not
be part of the lives and we talked about
paddle is no problem
Kamilah but really a way to structure
your program and then concurrency
pearlies will become like a side effect
when all this part karate you know in
independent tasks so simply said stuff
is happening at the same time is that
correct that's correct yes our problems
inherently concurrent or our solutions
concurrence well really the main idea is
how you can break the prompt the program
in a more independent in your work right
so really any probably come inherently
concurrent and said and parallelism
which you know aim to leverage the
resources of the day machine context and
improved the performance become like a
positive side effect right because now
we can have a programmed around and
leverage multi-core multi-core so really
a came applied to this solution and
benefit from concurrency because we can
design the code that is able also to
self adopt on the resource available on
the machine right so for example you can
write the program you know in a
concurrent structured manner so it can
run in a single cord however when you
run the same code in a multi-core
machine like for 816 well automatically
you know the program run faster because
able to self adopt and increase the
speed of monthly because leverage other
resources okay and this is little bit
confusing to me because there are so
many words and lingo around concurrency
and when I read your book you also
mention different words like concurrency
but also multi-threading multitasking
parallelism can you help the audience
figure out which is which so let's start
with the first one what is
multi-threading well so multitrader
really is a it's still part of the
family concurrency right is a is a form
of concurrency but multi try this base
like on on the same process when
multiple threads are running on the same
process so oh pretty much all the
programs are concurrent right but then
we can have it said different
kind of behavior and the like for
instance panel programming is also
concurrent but doesn't mean that
Concordia is also parallel so for
example parallelism in really based on
is constrained by the hardware okay
think about concurrent can be a problem
to run in a single core and true code
switching that the program the scheduler
run different part of the program
however in parallel programming you can
achieve parallelism or all it through
multi-core machines so really what
Elizabeth is concurrency in a multi-core
machine pretty much so parlays works
harder constraint multitasking is still
like concurrently but different from
multi-threading is the fact that you can
able to put thread to run on different
processes right so it doesn't mean you
know that these are multitasking or
running parallel but the period effect
delusion run in parallel because again
the scheduler can switch the bedtred
is a fusion between the deserve this
task okay so the three of them
multi-threading multitasking and
parallelism all are different forms of
concurrency yeah that's correct
right and the only form the only thing
is peril is mode is concurrent but is a
hard constraint hardware that's right
yeah god so really a exactly different
operation at the same time if they could
coracii more like give a delusion
can you give us some examples of typical
programs that you could address with or
that you should address with concurrent
solutions
sure so well really any sort application
that can benefit form partitioning
running parallel you know different
tasks in a multi-core machine for
example a videogame
financial stock trading image processing
machine learning also is very much you
know can be leveraged for parallelism
like a Muslim I did a little word
project in
in a neural network and we're really can
leverage quite well paralyze mode when
all you know the cell the network can be
computed at the same time and so these
days for instance one that these are
very trained is like think about
self-driving car there to make a
decision very quickly this you know can
be all computed in parallel to to
maximize the perform of the speed
because it's like life-saving kind of
decision right so really any sort of
modern software only today's require
high-performance computation right so
including the capability to produce a
great user experience from the UI back
to the you know back-end part of the
application when the computation
actually happened so and there also any
sort of algorithmic data you know can be
easily penalized actually a branch of
algorithmic or embarrass leap
parallelizable which means that it just
requires a little effort to be breaking
apart a random part of it like for
example there I can feel like the Monte
Carlo simulation of any sort of fractal
computation so yeah so a lot a lot of
stuff can be leveraged by can leverage
concurrency and in summary what I think
you're saying is parallelism is a good
or concurrency is a good solution when
you have a problem and you need speed
and it's easy to break it into separate
parts that can be calculated
independently from each other yes yes
just guys so the next question is why is
concurrency hard why are we devoting an
episode to this can you name some of the
things that make concurrency interesting
and hard
sure well the the main the main problem
is that still today mainstream languages
were not desirable components in mind
and and they probably know that back in
the day there was not the need to think
about having multiple thread random
multiple cores so this day although
we're facing this new challenge where we
have machine that
multiple course two to to be computed in
parallel and but this mainstream
languages there's still base or
mutational state and and that's my
problem when we have mutable state that
can be shared so at this point we have a
multiple trade that can access the same
memory slot and it can be lead to I want
to behavior such as race condition right
think about a trade to try to read the
same variable but the same value but
then trade one write the variable in
update the variable and then thread to
like is a value of the variable that is
not the latest one so you know you can
write in a water behavior and even you
know the the program can even crash if
you know it stream cases so the to
overcome this limitation visit this
problem they be introduced primitives
such as interlock screaming mutex
semaphore in these languages but as a
name apply lock it only prevent the
program parallel what really does
he protect this memory slot to be
corrupted to have like risk condition so
you like miss the point of paralyze your
code the libraries of the resources so
it also the dis lock is very complex to
use because in my he might protect his
memory slot from the access a multiple
thread but then with the program more
complex you can run another sort of bad
bad situation such as deadlock when to
trade are awaiting each other to release
a lock to continue the work so there
within each other in the program stop
stop the computation you know
indefinitely
and this is a probably the very hard to
the back right both freeze condition
deadlock because very hard to debug
especially because when you push the
code in production you can imagine that
the environment you run your local
machine when you write program your code
initially run differently than in
production that probably is a you know
more there to let's say
respond to a higher rate of
requestor is a under heavily stress
right so in my working on machinery
production this problem that then is
also very hard to reproduce on your
conversion at the back so there's a you
know different kind of problem it also
depend on on where the machine is
running right for instance I have a case
they happened a little while ago that
was very hard to investigate where the
the program was run in a machine that
actually were using plaintiff scheduler
which means that was practically when I
am a scheduler that ran a task and the
task is rather computational till the
end and but they was passed to a machine
that was using a competitive scheduler
which may use a contra switch in the
back to make the system more responsive
but for this kind of behavior really
there was somebody introduced in the
system that was now detected in a
beginning so it's very very it is a very
complex you know kind of programming
molecule course in general and very hard
to debug so in summary what you said is
one of the reasons that concurrency is
so hard is because programming languages
weren't really designed for concurrency
from the beginning so you run into
issues when you want to implement
concurrency in languages that weren't
really designed for it is that correct
that's correct yes that's correct so
yeah do they properly the share of state
the introduction then or primitive like
locks that can overcome this kind of of
issues but then introduced you know
extra complexity such as you know extra
overhead because you prevent us with the
product when the parallel and then it's
very hard to debug because as I
mentioned sometime in your local machine
was correctly but in different kind of
environment we different kinda scheduler
different kind of heavy stress work to
complete this is very hard to detect
right and as I said that when you run
this kind of problem in productions very
hard to reproduce especially you know
these you know this idea that the back
can disappear
when you also attempt to the bucket
right so they has a bad idea so I think
that we see this day that there's no
system was so they try to step back for
this kind of concurrent programming
because they are too much complexity and
they try to simplify it you know the
programming model for a developer that
can focus most on the logic rather than
know the complexity of concurrent
programming for instance one that is
very well known like is a noted not Jas
which actually is a provide a very high
throughput but it's really based on a
single threaded in an event loop single
threaded but what it does is that it
process all the incoming requests in a
io manner which is no input output which
is a not CPU bound operation so it's a
synchronous so is able to spawn and
compute main operation in in a
synchronous manner leveraging something
that is really key predicted CPU
light and I because single threaded I
really remove all the hazard that are
you know consequences from concurrent
program such as as I mentioned that lock
this condition and to actually have to
be able to run and in parallel you
actually spawn different kind of
different nodejs processes right so
easily they become too much complex so
redesign your content application to be
simple so what you're saying is rather
than doing concurrency in a programming
language it wasn't designed for it it
would be a better approach if
programming language designers would
solve the concurrent concurrency issues
in the programming language itself so
that it wouldn't be a problem for
programmers is that what you're saying
that's correct yes and we see these days
that more and more modern programming
languages are you know embracing this
kind of programming model so we have
like go for instance or rust there start
to introduce immutable structure
construct in a language so it become
immutables default like f-sharp Scala
and so forth they allow you to write a
mutable code but yet to be explicit so
it doesn't like like almost the opposite
that of mainstream programming language
like C++ Java C shot right let's take a
step back here because you mentioned a
bunch of interesting things most
specifically you said some languages
have immutability as a default but not
everyone might be familiar with what you
mean by that so could you explain that
what is what is immutability and what
does it have to do with concurrency yes
sure well so immutability idea that
whenever you assign a value bind a value
this value will never change and as you
can imagine as I mentioned one of the
problem with the kikuna programming is
the share or mutable state but now if
you share a state that can now change
well it become trying to save
intrinsically right because now because
the value would never change multiple
traffic analysis and without any problem
and even if from a mindset or the
programmer it can be challenging if you
come from an experience where you know
you've wrote imperative programming for
many many years which is based on
mutation of state but it really requires
a little bit of mindset in the beginning
and B investment and some had bad
headaches for sure but it's gonna be
paid off over time in fact as I said
even programming languages like Java and
c-sharp they were not designed with the
mutable structure now there are more and
more introducing discussed in the
language we could realize that the best
way to solve this kind of problem if
from the right we're moving completely
what could be the source of the problem
which is mutable state so you mentioned
something there about shared state being
the problem in concurrency could you
give an example of a problem where
shared state is the issue in a
concurrent solution sure well so any any
time that multiple thread can modify
a value that we share right so for
instance a very bad design you know call
you know shared global state but this is
a classic example where you share alike
a global counter and it's not protected
and your multiple requests coming in you
know in a server in appetit the counter
at the same time well it can happen that
the counter one reflected the real
number because the real value because
one thread can access and grab the value
and a second thread company changed the
values so now the second try to update
the value that was already be changed in
a race condition right so this is like
one of the classic problem of over is
condition
but how do we solve that with an
immutable data structure because how
would it would the alternative solution
look like because you have some shared
value that the both tracks need to write
to yes the both of them have an
immutable data structure how are we
going to consolidate the results of
let's say a MapReduce algorithm right
well so this is a question like as I
said it really become like a little bit
different mindset a change of mindset is
a different paradigm so if you come like
there are different kind approaches one
is definitely try to figure out a way to
redesign the program to avoid the change
in state or to avoid septuagint State
and leverage immutability one of the one
of the solution that whole technique use
for instance in a mutable structure
called component swap which is used
especially when design you know
concurrent algorithm to achieve
synchronization without the engagement
of disappointment of locks right a
company swap is in a low-level structure
that to work atomically and the compare
really the content or the value of a
memory slot within a given value and
they both have the same they modified
accounted in memory location with a new
value and this is said is done in a
single atomic operation and it's
guaranteed that each thread is gonna are
able to access to the latest in true
true value for example mean in.net it
was introduced a little while ago
immutable collection which is a bit
different for concurrent collection
amudha gradually the idea that whenever
you create this collection they would
never change
so if you add or remove an item a new
collection is created and to modify
actually these collection there is a
library that use underline technique
called the dimension the compare and
swap was the interesting though is that
we never use a immutable structure or
immutable collection you use something
called start
sharing property which is very cool
because now instead to create a copy
every time that you either remove an
item only change an item I shall really
leveraging immutability and instead to
create a new collection just create the
point at the reference state previous
collection with the updated value so at
this point relatability completely
embraces not just to remove the trade
hazard but also to reduce you know
memory consumption and memory pressure
and so forth so I think it's pretty cool
so slowly we're moving into talking
about data structure and you've just
mentioned the immutable collection are
there other examples of concurrent data
structures or structures that are really
useful if you're doing concurrent
programming yeah
so my for instance so there are two
different kind of collection like the
concurrent collection and immutable
collection the concurrent collection are
really designed to be to share State
among track but the challenge it become
when you build a structure that can
create more complexity because you wanna
really create this collection a very
performant so it's very hard to have you
know both benefit to be able to share
State among thread and also be able to
add high performance on the other side
has said immutable collection well
because the collection cannot change so
they are safe to be share mob thread
without you know penalty in performance
one of the most use concurrent
collection is the queue right because
use when actually queue that work to be
computed later when the resources are
available for instance one classic you
know and simple pattern they produce a
consumer palette so you have a producer
that you know queued up using a
concurrent keyword and some some items
and the other side the producer in a
different process of different trade
you're gonna pick up from this cute the
item in a you know twenty safe manner so
is this the same as a thread safe data
structure or is it concurrent data
different from a thread-safe data
structure not very similar and today is
a very subtle difference the main
difference they underlined lamentation
where trade safe is is if implemented
just to guarantee that there won't be
any sort of data corruption or rather
the other side the conquering of
structure has been implemented with the
more sophisticated algorithm to be to
guarantee also performance and for
instance cuneta structure can have
implemented a comparison
I'll go rhythm or they fall back to a
lock kind of approach if they're not be
able to compare swap the value then the
line value will you mutate at the
collection so they're just very complex
collection that guarantee also the
performance Thanks
digital ocean is the easiest cloud
platform to deploy manage and scale
applications of any size we're moving
infrastructure friction and providing
predictability so developers and their
teams can deploy faster and focus on
building software that customers love
with thousands of in-depth tutorials in
an active community we provide the
support you need digitalocean stands out
of the crowd due to its simplicity and
high performance with no billing
surprises try digitalocean for free by
getting a 100 dollar infrastructure
credit at doco /sc radio let's talk
about debugging because debugging needs
to be very hard in concurrent program in
the ending of the episode you're already
briefly meant the famous Heisenberg that
you cannot easily reproduce and if you
try the bug will change so can you can
you talk us through your typical
workflow when debugging a concurrent
program maybe you have an example a
recent example that you ran into where
you had to debug a concurrent issue what
was your problem
yeah so so first of all yes you're right
cookery program is very tough to the bug
and there are many different kind of you
know component and in and we of the spin
so there is auto friction to take care
recently I work in
is a rule engine application that
initially was designed to run multiple
validations for a set of records but the
idea that would just funny
many many many tasks like for one task
for each record to validate you can
imagine that was like thousand thousand
record so you so the application was
surely running slower the next equation
version application and the problems
that we would a lot extra overhead
introduced in application with external
context we chained and read the schedule
would you know going crazy to figure out
you know Wichitas Ryan is which into the
other and so forth so one of the
technique that they can be used first of
all is a abstracted wait did the program
to redesign it more than a grammar level
so I think that one one one application
to be designed to run in parallel before
to try to optimize the low-level
algorithm should be like think more
high-level and my furry said this
distribution of the work instead to have
like a multiple tasks you know run for
each record in in the case of the rule
engine and can be done more high-level
when you have like like a
producer/consumer part that was
mentioned earlier or this kind of no
redesign sorry this pattern it can be
helped you to redesign that application
and more high-level
and then when you you implement this
father you figure out we are at the
bottleneck of the application and then
you know keep continue to you know
redesign in leveraging parallelism to to
improve the performance and then you
start to never narrow down until you
finally know the low-level or we know
more it's more algorithm that can be
optimized so in this specific case I
breaking apart the pipeline each rule
engine instead to be twisted to run all
in a single thread it was each engine
was running separately so I'm really
using like a pipeline
pattern where each step of the pipeline
was able to consumer the resources and
not balance the work with the other step
of the pipeline and today by this kind
of plication the complexity became when
your multiple tread running parallel
because now whenever you you know set a
breakpoint
well you just stop or block the the in a
the current execution thread which mean
that you can stop there by the same time
in the background the other is if you
trade a steel ramen so if you try to
step forward to the next step of day to
the debugger most likely wallah you
won't hit the next line of the code that
you are currently by unigram in a
different part application where the
other thread is running and you start
you know control all the application and
it's not to be very complex so in this
case one approach is simple one you
really control the scheduler and be able
to set in a configuration level the
level of parallelism so in this case you
can adjust set a single-threaded so you
defeat the parallelism but it's still be
able to flow to the pipeline in step by
step and there are you know tools out
there that can help you definitely to
the back and in the multi node
application what I really like is is a
concurrent visualizer they actually is
able to run the application and provide
you like really a multi trademark map
and see how the application perform
visualization is correct
how did threats interact with each other
that's correct and this is very useful
because there are you know different
kind of cases where justified the graph
like a visual graph you can detect if
you have run in some sort of a bad
scenario such as I was saying earlier we
have many many tasks running more than
it should be you have something called
oversubscription which is a pattern that
they organized when you see the
scheduler stuff to call this which
multi-ball whole task in this when the
performance are be penalized by the
extra overhead another you know partly
organized to a graph is the lock convoys
when the lock they pretend
the memory slot he contain or restrain
the tread for a longer time then the
other trend uncommon interlock in there
waited a lot to be released so this will
be coming I said the convoy a lock so
you have multiple multiple tasks queued
up waiting then at least that is lowered
from from they arrived and that you it
visualizes tasks that are waiting for a
certain memory elements that's correct
yes and it is a great tool and of course
you cannot you know other you know be
like called old old-school kind of
approaches such as you can have very
sophisticated you know login trace where
actually you can log and detect this
this the stock of the trade and it's
ready you can create a snapshot of the
state with the oh the current thread
that ran in the process so you can
Allies test date so there are different
kind of technique that is very like
Silver Bullet that you mentioned are
there additional tools that you would
use to write logs or to analyze logs
from concurrent systems or is this used
good old-fashioned dumping in a text
file I'm reading it later
so it really depend the system that you
Ronnie there are tools that are helping
to create these trade dance so you can
analyze the tread after the around to
see the memories and the trade stocks
you know the memory is not is so forth
personally when I analyzed the performin
before even use like a concurrent tool
like as I said concurrency visualizer I
rather spend a little bit of extra time
in memory profilers right because this
actually that's sorta like been related
the two thing and one thing that we're
facing these days with manage code is
that some extra overhead are introduced
when there are too many color collection
generation in a problem right so a good
memory profiler is able to help you to
detect where there are too much memory
location in that especially in a
multi-threaded application this is also
you know that can imagine emphasized
because
multiple tread locating and you know
you're running different kind of problem
that's when the memory profiling can
help you to narrow down where at the
bottleneck or where at the situation
where there are too much location and
optimize that kind of part the code
suppose you would create a tool to help
debug concurrent programs you have
unlimited time and money you can hire
everyone what type of tool would you
build to improve the bugging concurrent
systems oh I don't like probably sorry I
have two tools in mind but what you know
if I use mainstream languages that you
know Shiro State did you force use
deadlock so it used locks I use like a
deadlock detector which actually pretty
much very hard to implement but I really
have time to try it but I I think it's
very hard to implement
however easier thing to do I think is
that again when we're leveraging
features such as immutability right and
or other property that referential
transparency and even explain what is it
properly I like to believe in future
that take to this proprietary compiler
should be able to detect them in this
say okay I'm safe I know that you know
that cause immutable it doesn't produce
side effect so I can optimize the code
for you and don't worry about everything
and something similar that actually
closure programming language is doing
right because again it's leveraging the
this property that is said ok this code
is is a deterministic so I could just
paralyze it for you without you to be
worried but again the code and to be
written using you know level it is
properly and that's where you know I'm a
believer you know in a functional
programming in this kind of a situation
because function programming it was not
only designed to be the Silver Bullet
for mother Elizabeth but really embrace
tenant such as mutability is the first
construct refused transparency and the
void or mutation state so really become
clearly the functional programming
really already used
these are the ingredients to write you
know correct concurrent program without
you know to be worried about all the
tread hazard that they are consequently
to imperative languages usual state so
you answered one of my questions already
secretly in there because one of my
questions was how do concurrency and
programming paradigms connect and you
already said functional programming is
really good for concurrent programming
because of the immutability we already
talked about and you also mentioned
referential transparency as a benefit of
functional programming languages could
you explain what that is and why it's a
benefit yeah sure so function
programming is a bit of the evaluation
of expression so and the idea that this
expression are without side effect okay
think about side effect as anything can
happen on the side from the function
whenever there's a change of state an
exception or you know any sort or
operation so something generally control
for example eye operation that you read
from a file system what I can produce
that effect because maybe they did the
file is not in a file system akin to an
exception right so any sort of function
where the output will it depend by the
input which means that every time you
pass the same put to a function the
output one change will be the same and
there should to not have a very
important property first of all because
this function depend by only the input
well you know you can cache the function
because the output will never change and
because again there is no side effect
the order diffusion is functionally
doesn't matter so it can really be
easily personalized so function
programming it doesn't make your code to
run faster but really able to structure
your program write your code to to be
ready to be paralyzed without any sort
of code changes right yeah so what
you're saying is
functional programming doesn't have side
effects and therefore you could take
functions and run them concurrent
because they will not interfere with
each other anyway because there are no
side effects right that's correct in in
a beginning I know as for today to me
concurrent application it is a way to
structure a program that can be or be
not really paralyzed but will either
give to breaking apart your your code in
independent task it very similar to
function programming well the idea
composition which is a something a
tenant but there is a very good property
about functional programming when you
breaking apart you know big problems is
more as more a function that are easy to
be solved directly and then you glue
them together with composition which is
very much similar to concurrence when
you run multiple tasks independently and
they be able to compose this task to
solve a more complex problem in parallel
so do you think it is the job of
programming language designers to solve
concurrency and that we will soon be in
a situation where concurrent problems
aren't hard anymore for programmers
because the language designers have
fixed concurrency and we can just
express everything in a regular
programming language without thinking
about concurrency that's my hope right
because it said I think that compilers
should be able to leverage this kind of
properly that make the program you know
run concurrently in a deterministic
manner
etcetera you know all the new modern
programming language that I see out
there they are it embracing these this
tenant right and who came late in a run
like you know mainstream language like
Java in c-sharp they're introducing
these this concept in a language right
so yeah I think a little like I don't
think gonna be a long time but are you
going to be part of the compiler able to
modify the code and making parallel for
you based on only know the proctor your
program but doesn't that take away the
freedom of the developer I want to
decide what trust my one process runs on
you're stealing my fun
well I you know I think that there would
be like for the most likely 80% of the
cases is gonna be covered by you know
that the compiler but I still hope that
they said that to be some still some
control left to the programmer to be
able to know to control would you do it
as I said like Scala F sharp this kind
of you know modern functional
programming languages I would say the
function of first programming languages
allowed you still to use mutable state
but you to be explicit right so it is
still it even will be a control right
there are some cases where mutability is
still you know a good approach to write
performant code to avoid you know extra
overhead and so forth I think that they
give you first as default a great tool
to write concurrent code and then allow
any ways to be explicit you know and
cheat or maybe you know still some some
some fancy Heather the technique to
leverage mutability and other sort of
programming model yeah I think they're
gonna be like both so suppose we have to
solve a concurrent problem in a
non-functional language in the old
language or an impressive programming
language is because it happens to be the
language that we use what are some of
the patterns from functional programming
that we could still use in in C or C++
to solve concurrent issues yeah so well
one problem that I see is that we should
be able to leverage immutability that
the problem with the leverage bit
ability in these programming languages
is that there is not only compiler the
Warnie on a you don't even read the code
immutable so there is a problem so still
left to the diligence of the developer
to be sure that code is thread safe
immutable but you can imagine this is
not always the case unfortunately but
you know there are some new technique
that are coming the these languages that
you actually tell the compiler that this
structure had to be immutable check for
me at least give a warning but other
technique is writing code
you know embracing the fugitive spare
transparency so really separate the pure
part of your program within pure part at
this point you know because you've
separated two kind of behavior to
function you can just focus on pure part
of the application they charge actually
when you're on your test
there is two paralyzed and so forth and
the immutable side of the applicants are
the impure side application it can be
left you know to a different kind of
technique optimization that probably
like recess immutable impure function
I won't even like focus on testing this
kind of function because most likely if
you write to the file system or read
from database well to me is not much
sense to test this kind of application
it also became very hard to to paralyze
due to the side effect so when you
separate the two kind of pure part with
a pure part you is the introduction of
concurrent application but you can focus
just on the pure aspect of your problem
and then what you're saying is in any
language you could write pure functions
or mainly pure functions and it will
still be beneficial for concurrent
programming even if you're not
programming in a pure FP language that's
correct just you know is a is a program
paradigm but pretty much you can embrace
registers very same it ability in almost
all language they would not design it
with this kind of paradigm in mind and
of course functional programming is
amazing people know I love functional
programming but a criticism we often
hear is that first programming doesn't
really scale but what if you want to
build a large system immutability is so
hard in the real world what would you
say to those people well I say that ok
this is really like a mind change of
mindset however there are some cases
that immutability or imperative program
is still make sense and I don't think
that is that the solution is both
extreme right I think that function
programming and in
the program you should really coexist in
your program rather Patino stay in in in
opposition so I think it makes sense
like right you know in functional
programming like when there are very
sophisticated or you know low level
algorithm they require you know
performance but imperative where
mutation makes sense like you know UI
application front-end application I
would say that it's nothing wrong with
that
right and what are some typical problems
we run into if you build large
concurrent systems apart from whether or
not we use functional programming
paradigm or functional programming ideas
what are typical problems we run into
with large concurrent system well one of
the challenge is really how detect in
partition the work that can be run in
part of it right so it is like bring
down to the the level of granularity or
dependent Lizabeth right so for instance
a fine-grained panel is not really in
facilitating
work to be balanced between you know
different tread and this case the
program is a partition broken different
kind of many different many small tasks
however the challenge here that if you
had too many tasks as mentioned early
you can run a situation we have way too
many tasks random pattern but on the
other side if you try to have more a
coarse grain pattern is mode so you
split the task in a bigger size like the
larger then the de Malabo computation
take knockin taking place in processor
but also you ran in situation where very
few tasks so you don't real everage all
the resources so there are different
kinds of challenges and then generally
again not really silver bullet but
measure measure measure
ever you know run your application as it
is have a baseline so you can determine
it
the goal in how to improve your program
and then make the changes in pre measure
and see actually if you change will
improve in order to the performance so
really
side which side of the gravel level
optimization you should change the
change of code but always measure
measure measure it is always a good idea
I think to measure even in a non
concurrent single trailer program yeah
one thing I learned from your book that
I thought was really insightful is the
idea of concurrent design patterns could
you explain to the audience what a
concurrent design pattern is and maybe
name one or two examples of concurrent
design paths sure well you know pattern
are always great because it creates you
know additionally a language you know
between developers so they know what
they're talking about
and there are different kind of design
pattern also concurrent design pattern
that generally branch in their group in
family like divisor concur is one very
common use when again you break a
problem in smaller part that can be
solved like in a very cool civil manner
like when you work a tree as a tree
structure in part of it right that that
could be something that can be solved a
course syllabus and in a concordant
manner and then other pattern like a day
the fork/join pattern is a very commonly
used that I think that they use some
time even that developers don't know is
using it like for instance there are
like the parallel for each loop the same
approach that you know spawn multiple
tasks partition the computation and they
enjoy the result in aggregate that is
off to right and in a higher scale a
high-level scale for to join pattern can
be you know consider like part of the
the MapReduce pattern when you know you
you might produce your your data your
data and really each step of the
computation you can use like a fork
joint father use for multiple tasks and
you rejoin its father a joint you know
in each step for your MapReduce which is
called MapReduce but it's not just my
producer it can be different kind of
standard computation so definitely is a
cocoon a powder
and something that can solve your
problem so
there are some cases that shoe some
pattern make more sense than other right
and that's pretty no the dll is assetid
if you run like in data panel is much
when you are like single structure to be
performed against multiple data probably
for the join is a great pattern or the
the probabilitor was mentioned earlier
with the rule engine when you can use a
pipeline pattern where each step of the
pipeline it can be considered like a
smaller subset or producer-consumer but
allowed you to load balance the work
among each step of the pipeline in a
concurrent manner
so are these concurrent design patterns
concurrent versions of let's say normal
design parents existing design patterns
or are they entirely new design parent
patterns that have no relationship to
existing ones it's a good question these
are both like there are some powder that
are you know traditional powder that can
be that cook or escape introduce another
sure that you know adjust part of the
concurrent pattern right
for instance divided concur as I
mentioned is a is a pattern that can be
used for recent to user to solve them
what's in it the quicksort algorithm
right a quicksort can be either
sequential or concurrent right on the
other side there are pattern like
scatter and gather where you scared a
lot information there's an entirely
different kind of system and then when
leverage you know sort of computation
around in different machine that night
and so forth and then when they complete
they send you back the result that you
can aggregate so it's a bit about some
of them are versions and other ones are
entirely unrelated that's correct
one more thing that I want to talk about
is asynchronous programming or reactive
programming we already touched upon
async a little bit when we were talking
about the architecture of node which is
single threaded by design can you
explain what asynchronous programming is
and how it relates to concurrent
programming yes asynchronous programming
have a very cool
Proctor hm but think about sickles
programming as a computation that we
complete later in the future you don't
know when but you're not going to be
completed there are some cases that it
can be notified so when you start the
computation the computations start in
big computing a different tribe and they
the main try to be notified when the
computation is completed true maybe like
a callback that is quite enough it's
quite popular or but there are other
cases like for instance it can be like a
final forget
so you just send the operation and you
don't care about the result but what is
cool about the synchronous programming
is that based on IO bound operation
which means is mean evolve just a little
bit of CPU computation charge so really
leave the CPU like to do other operation
because the idea is that the second
operation is going to be computed
somewhere else for instance our web
request right you send a web request
they're going to be computing problem a
different service which is pretty cool
because now we can leverage a property
to like to call unbounded parallelism
and say abundant partly smug because
when I talk about parallelism mode is
like concurrency but with harden
constraint so parallelism or Quran only
in a multi-core machine however a
synchronous programming due to the fact
that the computation ran somewhere else
well you can achieve true parallelism
mode even a single code machine right
because you can spot thousand of a
single operation on a single core
machine there to be compute in a
different place and then just you know
receive a notification when they
complete and continue the work so I
think that's a very cool property about
a synchronous programming in which you
know step further is a really is is that
the base programming model to implement
in a scalable system which mean is
system they're able to cope to many many
requests at the same time because again
it's not really bow to the CP or a
source that you have but just to IO IO
resources
so this is very cool the other thing
that you would say about interactive
programming it kind of connected to a
synchronous programming because it
allowed you to treat the stream of a
synchronous event right
but likeliness in a way that you would
do operation with a collection price
really bring up the composable aspect of
this operation so you can iterate it to
these stream of a synchronous bank which
the match of data like you know in array
like like word like an array or list and
so forth so really we have two
programming free you from handling
complex code back from a secret
programming and make your code no more
readable and less prone to bugs and easy
to understand but reactive programming
modules or libraries exist in many
mainstream programming languages
nowadays also known functional
programming languages like JavaScript
for example how does this fit into your
story of functional programming is best
for concurrent program well so I think
that the reactive programming is a just
no app atom that can be replaced any
sort developed it observable pattern but
what is great about reactive programming
is that I like to think a program is the
almost a can be like the both they had a
detail of your concurrent program one
part can be the part of your program
that said data to your algorithm the
kernel concurrently but also that other
side of the algorithmic and you can feel
reactive programming you know with this
event and just manipulate event to to
ultimately you know aggregate the result
do something with your result right
aggregate the result filter the result
and so forth there are actually a very
cool library that though is based on an
agent programming model which is a
message passing programming model but
the idea is that whenever the agent
receive a message
compute a message and then send out the
result and then you can plug grantee
programming to receive this message and
do something in a more you know
composable or functional manner right so
you just mentioned message passing as
another pattern maybe not everyone is
familiar with this model could you
explain what is a message passing
approach so message passing is a base on
our old idea where instead to share a
state is or you know the department of
program communicate the charter only
through messages and this brings in that
the idea of a actor or agent there are
subtle different there but the these are
very small you know computation that
communicate only through messages which
mean that they are isolated because now
these inner computation the trigger just
single threaded right so if this is no
computation a single try that you just
remove all the complexity to to
concurrency so the parallelism mode is
achieved by having many many actor or
agent they communicate each other
through you know message passing which
again the message you get best with both
word the message is immutable
okay so cannot change but also the agent
are protected because being single
threaded
you can even check on agent that
destroyed safe intrinsically because
only the agent can access this state
information because let's say is a
single traded you were running sort of
race condition so it's a great
programming model because you can
structure your code really you know
small unit that you can pass the
messages like sort of like great for the
pipeline approach we mentioned earlier
so each agent can spawn so they can send
a message to the next step of the
pipeline which is an agent in peril is
mode is achieved in this case by having
multiple agent run or for each step of
the pipeline but this is transferred by
the developer so you just send a message
to the next step and when you send a
message the agent Astrid is able to load
balance the work
other agent that a part of the the step
of the pipelining
so how agents based programming relates
to concurrent programming is that you
can have a system in which agents are
send each other messages which are
immutable and every agent would have its
own thread so that's trad save by
default do i summarize that correctly
that's correct yes okay so lots to
choose from in concurrent programming we
can have programming languages that
solve the issue or immutable data
structure or agents is there anything
you want to add as possibilities that
people should consider if they have a
concurrent situation at hands sure so so
when you wrote the program I think a
mutability is a great tool by self to
achieve a better solution or easy
solution we say no better but these are
like the share nothing approach like the
mess of passing we just talk right and
we say these days this this has become
also like a in architecture kind of
approach like we have a micro services
that pretty much don't share step
between other micro services we have the
idea of the secure s pattern comment
queries possibility civil segregation
where actually this father the ideas
that separate the part of when you read
only party application to their
publications actually writing a side
effect and when you actually split this
kind of a party program because you
share nothing
this actually become easier not just to
reason about your program but easy to
introduce parallel Elizabeth because now
is easy to task the but for the
specific part of code that don't produce
side effect because it will share state
or you can decide well instead to task I
want to use
agents right so at that point you can
introduce agent easily because either to
worry about the part your program the
great side effect because already are
separated and in a read-only manner so
they can be easily spawn multiple aging
without you know run-in I want the
behavior in your code Sara
deterministically so that's a good
approach there to start thanks I'm all
out of questions I think I've asked
everything I wanted to know is there
anything more you want to
well first I want to thank you to Adam
here I think we cover a lot of material
yes and yeah I mean I think that we can
post something a new website with some
other resources that can prepare for the
listener so we'll definitely link to
your book of course there's there any
any other place on the web where people
can read more about you and your work
well there are a great video I think
that personally I really love
message-passing concurrent programming
model so it that's it's a great you know
paradigm to start with to write you know
concurrent program I will start in in
them either way and start to look around
this kind there are many resources out
there is very fertile which is one the
best which one off but definitely that's
what I try to motivate the listener to
start investigate the message
specifically mother
okay thanks thanks a lot for being on
the show Ricky thank you for anybody
digitalocean is the easiest cloud
platform to deploy manage and scale
applications of any size we're moving
infrastructure friction and providing
predictability so developers and their
teams can deploy faster and focus on
building software that customers love
with thousands of in-depth tutorials and
an active community we provide the
support you need digitalocean stands out
of the crowd due to its simplicity and
high performance with no billing
surprises try digitalocean for free by
getting a 100 dollar infrastructure
credit at doco /sc radio thanks for
listening to Nessie radio an educational
program brought to you by Archer police
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at SC radio slack calm you can
also email us at team @ SC - radio net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening